# 大家好 我去抓點那個笋蟲
Hi everyone! I'm gonna catch some, some bamboo shoots weevils,
# 笋蟲來 補充一下蛋白質 (原字幕不見了)
some weevils to replenish me with protein.
# 最近老是腰酸背痛
The back pain is always attacking me these days.
# 那邊 笋蟲就喜歡待在那種地方
There. The bamboo shots weevils like staying in those places.
# 你看 笋蟲就生活在嫩的竹笋上面
Look! The weevils are living on the young bamboo shoots.
# 它吸竹笋的汁
They suck the juice from the bamboo shoots.
# 它是壞蛋來的 害蟲來的
They are bad guys, pests!
# 都沒有 是不是看到我來啦 它們都全跑啦
I can't see any of them. Have they all run away, cuz they saw me coming?
# 一個都沒有哦
Not even one here
# 這個笋蟲的種都可能被 去年被我們抓完啦
Perhaps we've already caught the last, the last weevil last year.
# 這裡深山老林一樣
Here's like a deep, wild and ancient forest.
# 這 那麼多草
Here's so much weeds.
# 你看 找了好久 只找了一找了一個
Look! After a long time, we've found, found only one.
# 抓起來
Let me catch it.
# 我忘了它好大的力氣
I've forgotten that it grabs very strongly.
# 看你的力氣大還是我的力氣大
Let's see who's stronger, you or me.
# 這個是害蟲來的哦 專吃這個竹子的汁啊
This is pest, you know. It eats nothing but the juice from bamboos.
# 壞的很
They're really bad.
# 你看 它現在跑不了啦 可以 可以透氣的這裡
Look! Then it can't run away now. The air, the air can pass through here.
# 再去看一下有沒有 一個不夠吃啊
Let's see if there are any more. One is not enough.
# 應該 附近應該有的 還有的
There should be, should be some more nearby. There should be more.
# 不可能有一個的 要有也有一對呀
It can't be just one. Two makes much more sense.
# 你看 這塊竹笋 就是被那個笋蟲吃的 咬了幾個口
Look! This bamboo shoot, has been eaten by the weevils. There are a few bites.
# 它們壞的很
They're really bad guys.
# 就把那個竹子汁都吸乾啦 這棵竹子都可能會死掉
They've sucked all the juice from this bamboo. It might not survive.
# 你看 又抓到一個
Look! One more here.
# 還在 可能還 它還在睡覺
It's still, it may be still, still sleeping.
# 這個蟲子炸了很好吃的 誒耶 哦尿的
This weevil is really tasty when it's fried. Aya, it pisses.
# 等一下來
A moment
# 那瓶子裝起來
Put it in the jar.
# 這個用油炸一下或者烤一下都很好吃的
Fried or grilled, it's really tasty.
# 你看 就抓了兩個
Look! So you've caught just two.
# 我看下明天我再去找一下看能不能找的到
l think I'll be coming again tomorrow and see if there are any more.
# 再搞一點來 太 太少啦
I want a little more. It's too, too few.
# 不夠吃啊
It's not enough.
# 好啦 先回去啦
Alright! Let's go back first.
# 你看 抓了一天 才抓了四個 怎麼吃 太少啦
Look! I spent a whole day only to have caught just four. What should I do? It's too few.
# 去 檢一點田螺來湊 湊一點田螺才
I'm gonna, pick some river snails to make it a meal. Without some river snails,
# 才夠 夠吃
it won't be, won't be enough.
# 就在河邊檢一下
We're heading to the riverside.
# 過來
Come here!
# 快點快點
C'mon, c'mon!
# 剛好來到這裡 搞點這個薄荷回去
It just so happens that I pass by here. Let me get some mint back home.
# 這薄荷都已經開花啦
The mint has already blossomed.
# 嗯 好濃的味道
Um! A rich scent of mint
# 你看 這個是草來的
Look! This is grass.
# 一聞都聞的出這個味道
I can tell immediately by the smell.
# 在野外摘東西要摘 摘對來哦 有時會摘錯的
While in the wild, it's important to pick the right things. Sometime we may pick the wrong things,
# 那就不好啦
and it's too bad.
# 夠啦夠啦 嗯 這個就是薄荷
Enough, enough. Um. This is mint.
# 剛好衣服都濕完啦
My clothes are already soaked now.
# 直接坐在河裡面去
Let us just sit in the river.
# 啊~
Ah~
# 舒服啊
Wonderful!
# 你看 天氣熱 在水裡面走 走水路 很不錯的哦
Look! When it's hot, walking in the water, through a water path, is really not bad, you know.
# 你看 又不要用力 輕輕的蹬兩下就好啦
Look! I don't need to do anything, except pushing a few times very slightly.
# 它這水太淺了
The water here is too shallow.
# 很舒服的哦 這樣
It's so nice, in the water.
# 它這裡太淺啦 老是刮底盤
It's too shallow here. The bank is always scratching me.
# 在深一點的地方就可以
I would be better with deeper water.
# 褲子濕了 衣服也濕了
My pants are soaked, and so is my T-shirt.
# 你看這頭牛 偷吃我的象草哦
Have a look at these cows. They're stealing my elephant grass.
# 誰家的 讚到我家這裡來
Whose cows are they? Why do they come to my place?
# 摸一下
Let me touch you.
# 你看 這一片象草都是我種的 這些都是今年剛種下的 紅的
Look! The whole area of elephant grass here is mine. I planted them this year, the red ones.
# 這明年就很多啦 這一片都是
There will be a lot next year, covering the whole area.
# 下面的那個 白的象草 那一坨象草 你看 多茂盛啊
Those down there, the white elephant grass, that bunch of elephant grass. Look! It's so bushy.
# 搞兩條牛 搞兩條牛回來食都可以把它養大
I can fetch a couple of cattle, fetch a couple of cattle and raise them here.
# 那麼多草 夠了
There's so much grass. It must be enough.
# 這田螺 很靚哦
These river snails, are really beautiful!
# 等一下就乾淨了
They will be clean in a while.
# 洗一點這個米水 泡一下這個田螺
I'm gonna get some, some rice water. I'll soak the snails in it.
# 我們這些 家裡的大米 自己碾出來的
This is our, home grown rice. We milled them ourselves.
# 都是 這個米水都是乳白色的
It's like, the rice water is always milky white,
# 像牛奶一樣
just like milk.
# 你看 開始啦 這個米水它們不適應它就
Look! It starts. They don't like the rice water, so they're,
# 身上的泥 它就 把它的身子伸出來
the mud on their bodies, they're squeezing out their bodies,
# 伸出來之後身上的泥就會吐出來哦
and then they'll, spit out the mud on their bodies.
# 看上這個
Have a look at this one!
# 這個沒事的 沒毒的 只是它們不適應而已
It's not a problem, not poisonous. It's all because it doesn't like the rice water.
# 3小時後
Three hours later
# 你看 這些都是
Look! These are all,
# 田螺的那個
the cracked shells from the,
# 田螺瞉
from the river snails,
# 碎的田螺瞉
the cracked snail shells.
# 你看 掉了好多泥
Look! They've spitted out a lot of mud.
# 用那個摟一下
Let me rinse them with the, you know.
# 你看 現在很乾淨了哦 一點泥味都沒有了
Look! It's very clean now. Not even a bit of the smell of mud remains.
# 去一下它屁股
Let's get rid of their butts.
# 把它屁股剪掉
I'm gonna cut away their butts.
# 這個好剪
This pincer is nice.
# 搞點這個生薑下去
I put some, some ginger here.
# 你看 這田螺 溫水煮田螺
Look! The river snails, boil the snails, slowly in warm water.
# 你看這些田螺 毫無反抗能力
Have a look at the river snails. They simply can't resist at all.
# 這煮出來的湯都沒甚麼 看上去都沒甚麼泥 泥巴味
There's hardly any, I can't see any mud, any smell of mud in the water.
# 乾淨啦
It's clean now.
# 把它撈起來啦
Let me take them out.
# 去清水洗一下
Wash them with fresh water first.
# 洗洗 洗洗它的身子
Let me wash, wash their bodies.
# 把這些料搞香 再把田螺放下去
I fry the side ingredients first, and then put the river snails.
# 把這田螺放下去啦
Now it's time for the river snails.
# 放點鹽
Put some salt.
# 稍微放鹹一點
I want a bit more salt.
# 加點這個薄荷
Put some, some mint.
# 加點老抽和生抽哦
I'm putting some dark and light soy sauce.
# 這是老抽 這是生抽
This is the dark one, and this is the light one.
# 要放點水 放點水把它煮乾那個水就好啦
I gotta put some water. It will then be done when the water dries out.
# 等下 直接大火收汁
I'll then, thicken the sauce on high heat.
# 哇 這田螺好啦
Wa! The river snails are ready now.
# 你看 經過一下午的努力
Look! With the effort in the whole afternoon,
# 做了一個菜
a dish is completed.
# 就這個菜
It's this one.
# 田螺
River snails
# 挑個最大的來吃
Let me pick the biggest one.
# 你看 這個
Look! This one
# 嗯 可以
Um! Not bad!
# 好啦 我去看一下那個笋蟲
Alright! Let me take a look at the weevils.
# 趁現在還有火哦 我把笋蟲烤啦
I'm gonna grill the weevil, before the fire goes off.
# 起來啦起來啦 準備上刑場啦
Wake up, wake up! Time to go to the fire stake!
# 把它的腳去掉
I remove its legs,
# 把它的腳去掉 把頭去掉
remove its legs, and also its head,
# 就可以吃啦
then the rest is edible.
# 這頭也要去掉
The head needs to be removed as well.
# 這翅肪也要去掉 翅肪不好吃的 你看
The wings need to be removed as well. The wings don't taste good. Look!
# 同樣的來 再來一個
The same steps. Next one.
# 誰來 就你長的大一點
Who's coming? You're the bigger one.
# 哎呦 它要咬人一樣
Aya! It wants to bite.
# 戳的我好痛
It stings me. It hurts.
# 你看 戳著我的手
Look! It stings my finger.
# 臨死掙扎
Final struggle
# 我也知道啊 那誰叫你的
I know. But who asked you to be,
# 你的營養有那麼好嘞 是不是 它勾著我了 不放
to be so nutritious, right? It hooks on me. It's not going away.
# 放開我
Off your legs!
# 放不放
Are you listeing?
# 你敢飛嗎
Dare you fly away?
# 它又不敢飛
It dares not.
# 你看 它死都不放哦 一直抱著我
Look! It's grabbing me with all its might, grabbing my,
# 把著我的 小手
grabbing my, tiny finger.
# 你看這個還會動哦 沒事
Look! This one is still moving. No worries.
# 等下要 先烤一下 撒點鹽撒點油 嘖 就可以吃啦
I'll then, grill it for a while, spray some oil and some salt. Then it will be ready to serve.
# 你看 這裡還有一點火
Look! Here's still a little bit fire.
# 這樣就不用 不用生火
Then I don't need to, start another fire.
# 搞點油
Put some oil.
# 再撒點鹽
And then some salt.
# 雨路均沾 一人沾一點
To be fair, everybody has its share of salt.
# 哇 搞的好香啊
Wa! It smells so good!
# 好香啊 這味道出來啦
It smells so good! The flavour is coming out.
# 好多鹽 先洗一下
Too much salt. Let me wash it.
# 你看 直接烤熟了哦
Look! It's done right away.
# 夾一下它
Hold it here.
# 哇 你看肉 (註︰不知道昆蟲用"meat"是否適合，但找不到更好的字了)
Wa! Have a look at the meat.
# 好香啊
It smells so good!
# 真的
Really good!
# 你看 這些渣渣
Look! Here's the residue.
# 蛋白質豐富 瘦肉
Rich in protein. Lean meat.
# 嗯 可以
Um! Not bad!
# 它頭沒有 沒有肉
There's nothing to eat, in the head.
# 真的 感覺像有點雞肉味一樣
No kidding. It really tastes a bit like chicken.
# 好香啊 攝影哥 攝影小哥還小的時候經常吃這個
It smells so good. Mr. Camra, Mr. Cameraman used to eat a lot of these when he was small.
# 口味太重啦
He was simply too exceptional.
# 這種是害蟲
These are pest.
# 吃起來 就是好啦
But they're so nice, as food.
# 你看 這個是肉哦 有點像瘦肉 看到沒有
Look! This is lean meat. It's a bit like lean meat. See?
# 嗯 味道還可以 來 嘗一個
Um! It tastes not bad. C'mon! Try one!
# 今天的視頻就到這這裡啦
The video ends here.